Guide to the Cedric Belfrage Papers TAM.143
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Political prisoners -- United States.; Reviews (document genre); Socialists |z England.; Translators |z England.; Authors, English.; Journalists |z New York (State) |z New York.; Radicalism -- United States.; Journalists |z England.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Film critics |z England.; Audiocassettes.; Periodical editors -- United States.; New Left.; Fascism.; Soviet Union.; Developing countries.; Cuba.; Videocassettes.; Correspondence.; Peace movements -- United States.; Typescripts; Photographs.; Socialists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Cuernavaca (Mexico); Cold War.; Sharecroppers |z Missouri.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; Political activists |z California |z Hollywood (Los Angeles, Calif.).; Journalists |z California |z Hollywood.; Anti-fascist movements |z Germany.; Manuscripts; Secret service |z New York (State) |z New York.; Civil rights movements -- United States.; Journalism, Socialist -- United States; Latin America.; Press agents |z England |z London.; Film critics |z California |z Hollywood.; Hollywood (Los Angeles, Calif.); Anti-communist movements; Antisemitism.; Dreiser, Theodore, 1871-1945; Fromm, Erich, 1900-1980; Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014; Robinson, Joan.; National Guardian; Great Britain. MI6; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Middleton, Peggy; Belfrage, Ann; Belfrage, Sally, 1936-; Belfrage, Mary Bernick; Middleton, Hannah; Loesser, Frank, 1910-1969; Zapata, Emiliano, 1879-1919; Du Bois, Shirley Graham, 1896-1977; Galeano, Eduardo H., 1940-; Carlebach, Emil; Casas, Bartolomé de las, 1474-1566; Sheiner, Leo; MacKenzie, Scotty; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; Sobell, Morton; Rosenberg, Ethel, 1915-1953; Rosenberg, Julius, 1918-1953; Strong, Anna Louise, 1885-1970; Zilliacus, K. (Konni), 1894-1967; McManus, Jack; Whitfield, Owen.; Snow, Thad, 1881-1954; Wallace, Henry.; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971.; Goldwyn, Samuel, 1882-1974.; Beaverbrook, Max Aitken, Baron, 1879-1964; Williams, Claude.; Aronson, James; Burchett, Wilfred G., 1911-1983; Till, Emmett, 1941-1955; Durr, Virginia Foster; Braden, Carl, 1914-1975; Braden, Anne, 1924-2006; Frankfurter Rundschau; Progressive Party (U.S.: 1948); Allied Forces. Supreme Headquarters. Psychological Warfare Division; Spanish Republican Committee (U.S.); Hollywood Anti-Nazi League; Clipper (Hollywood, Calif.); National Paul Robeson Committee (U.S.); Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); Hiss, Alger; Lamont, Corliss, 1902-1995.
- Series I: Biographical Materials, 1922-1990
  Scope and Content Note
  Biographical Materials (1922 - 1990) is the smallest portion of the collection. It contains personal notes, passports and other identification, engagement diaries and obituaries.
  - Miscellaneous notes and writings., undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Passports, identification cards, press and literary contact list., 1922-1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Engagement diaries., 1957, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C.B. obituaries., 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cedric Belfrage: Portraits in Pencil [signed "Buenos Aires, Shan...? (name of artist)], 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4A)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1937-1989
  Family Correspondence is mostly from his daughters Sally and Anne, and Anne's mother Anne-Marie. Most of the topics covered by these letters are personal, relating to family matters, arranging visits, and the goings-on of everyday life. Sally's career as a writer and Anne's as a linguist are also well documented, and they often write about Belfrage's writing projects, helping to find publishers or offering criticism. Sally's participation in the Student Non-violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and her 1964 summer in Mississippi as a civil rights activist about which she wrote her first book, Freedom Summer, is covered in detail. There is also a short but interesting correspondence between Anne (who grew up in Paris) and Belfrage about the worker and student uprising in Paris in May 1968, especially regarding the role of the Communist Party. Most of the correspondence from Belfrage's son, Nick, is about his love life and his career as a wine taster. There is also correspondence from Belfrage's sister-in-law, Joyce Belfrage, regarding the poor health of his brother, Bruce.
  General correspondence is mostly with political colleagues discussing their and Cedric's writing projects, current events, and developments in leftist and socialist movements. The primary correspondent in this section in Jim Aronson (1955 - 1990). While this correspondence is mostly incoming, there is a substantial amount from Belfrage to Aronson. They discuss mostly personal issues such as health, family, and their respective publishing projects. They also write about the problems of the National Guardian (see Wilfred Burchett correspondence and the National Guardian section for more) and current events. In 1979, while Aronson is teaching journalism in Peking, they have a major disagreement about China's presence in Vietnam that threatens their friendship.
  Another primary correspondent is Claude Williams (1938-1980), a southern Marxist Christian preacher and the founder of The People's Institute of Applied Religion, about whom Belfrage wrote a biography (appearing variously as Let My People Go, 1937; South of God, 1938, A Faith to Free The People, 1944). This correspondence is mostly about Claude's work and his collaborative unfinished book project with Belfrage, The People's Book, aka, The Scarlet Thread, a revolutionary reading of the Bible. Belfrage also corresponds with Paul Robeson (1956-1965) regarding the National Paul Robeson Committee (this correspondence is mostly with the secretary of this committee, Frank Loesser). Related to the Robeson correspondence is the correspondence of sisters Hannah and Peggy Middleton (London County Council Member for Greenwich, and Labour candidate for Parliament). This consists of letters from Peggy to Hannah about Robeson. Included are notes by Belfrage on this correspondence. W.E.B. DuBois and his wife Shirley Graham (1955-1964) correspond with Belfrage about DuBois's world tour, and a tribute to DuBois that Belfrage helps organize.
  The correspondence with organizations is mostly with journals, magazines and newspapers regarding the publication of Belfrage's articles and letters to the editor. Among the journals is Third World, of which Belfrage was an editor. There is also a short but interesting correspondence with the South Paddington Labour Party (1956-1957) in which Belfrage debates whether or not to join and elaborates on his reasons for not wanting to sign an oath of "political purity."
  The second section of general correspondence is arranged alphabetically by country or region of origin. It is mostly with friends and political colleagues about personal issues such as health, family and career, but there is also discussion of politics and current events.
  Africa: The main figures in the African section are Conor Cruise O'Brien, the Irish Vice Chancellor of the University of Ghana about 'black native power,' and Alfred Kgokong of the African National Congress regarding Belfrage's support of that organization.
  Asia: The key writer from the Asian section is Anna Louise Strong who was the National Guardian correspondent in Peking during the 1960's.
  Australia/New Zealand: This section contains only a few letters. Among them are a letter on Belfrage's behalf by John Baker to the Australian Broadcasting Commission regarding publicity for The American Inquisition, a letter from Disarmament Research Group in Australia asking for a Cuban contact, and two letters from Noel Wilson of New Zealand regarding Jamaican trade unionist Ferdinand Smith.
  Canada: The major figures from the Canadian correspondence are Sol Pomerance, Beryl Wheelon (regarding Castro and Cuba) and Betty Madiros of the Socialist Fellowship Seminar where Belfrage spoke on Latin American politics. This correspondence also pertains to surgery that Belfrage had in Canada in 1975 and 1979.
  Caribbean and Central America: This section features Rosa Hilda Zell, the Cuban poet, and Steve Nelson of the Libreria El Porvenir in Costa Rica who write often of their respective projects. Europe: Comprised mainly of letters from France and Germany. The main correspondents are Wilfred Burchett who writes from Paris in the late 1960's, Victor Grossman of the Deutsche Akademie Der Kunste Zu Berlin in Berlin regarding a donation to the Paul Robeson archive (1966), and Franz Loesser regarding his book on the Rosenbergs (1975-76).
  Ireland/United Kingdom: Contains correspondence between Belfrage and K. Zilliacus about the Soviet-Yugoslav conflict (1950), the Cold War and the National Peace Party (1950's), Cuba (1962), and the British Labor Party (1965). Also in this section Belfrage corresponds with Joan Robinson (a Cambridge professor) (5/76) about China's position on Angola, Clive Jenkins of the Association of Scientific, Technical and Managerial Staff, and Heinrich Fraenkel of The New Statesman.
  Mexico: Clive B. Smith and Charles Small are the main correspondents in the Mexico section. Small writes about the Chilean political situation, and on behalf of refugees. In 1973 he has an argument with Belfrage over his review of The American Inquisition. There is a short series of letters in 1963 from Carlos Fuentes about Cedric renting his apartment in Mexico.
  South America: This section is mostly in Spanish. It contains several letters from the Peoples' Progressive Party in British Guyana about articles by Belfrage for them, from Harry Drayton of the University of Guyana about the political situation in that country, and from Maurice Bazin in Brazil about Brazil and Portugal.
  United States: This is the largest section. Some of the prominent figures from whom Belfrage receives letters are Theodore Dreiser and Erich Fromm in the 1940's, Anna Louise Strong in the 1950's, Rockwell Kent in the 1960's, Alger Hiss in the 1970's, Virginia Durr and Serge Chermayeff in the 1980's, and Pete Seeger (undated). Some of the most frequent U.S. correspondents are Lorna D. Smith regarding the Civil Rights movement in the south and Stokeley Carmichael, Maxwell Geismar regarding his writings, politics and U.S. leftist periodicals, and Decca Treuhaft. Some of the major topics covered are events in Cuba in the early 1960's, Theodore Dreiser's death (1963-64), the endorsement of McGovern's presidential campaign (1972), Third World leftist politics (c.1979-1981), and Belfrage's participation in the Meiklejohn Civil Liberties Union "Are You or Have You Ever Been?" symposium (1980). In an outgoing letter (Sep 1974) to Carl Braden Belfrage discusses Marxism, revolution and party organization.
  - Subseries II:A: Family Correspondence, 1953-1987
    - Anne Belfrage/Zribi & Anne-Marie Hertz., 1959-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Anne Belfrage/Zribi & Anne-Marie Hertz., 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Anne Belfrage/Zribi & Anne-Marie Hertz., 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Sally Belfrage/Pomerance., 1955-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Sally Belfrage/Pomerance., 1964-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Sally Belfrage/Pomerance., 1980-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Nick Belfrage., 1955-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Mother's Death., 1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Family., undated, 1953-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subseries II:B: General Correspondence - Individuals, 1938-1988
    - C.B. to Jim Aronson., 1959-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - C.B. to Jim Aronson., 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - C.B. to Jim Aronson., undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Jim Aronson to C.B., 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Jim Aronson to C.B., 1963-1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Jim Aronson to C.B., 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Jim Aronson to C.B., 1980-1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Jim Aronson to and From Others., 1963-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Jim Aronson Writings., 1945, 1970-1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Anne Braden re: Southern Conference Educational Fund., 1973 (Box 3, Folder 4a)
    - Wilfred Burchett., 1965-1976 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Emil Carlebach., 1945-1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Noam Chomsky., 1970-1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Martin Duberman., 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - W.E.B. Dubois and Shirley Graham., 1955-1964 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Richard Hart., 1963-1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Hiss, Alger, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 10A)
    - Annie and Malcolm Macewen., 1972-1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Magazines, Journals & Newspapers., 1946-1969 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Magazines, Journals & Newspapers., 1970-1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Peggy and Hannah Middleton., 1961-1975 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Monthly Review Press., 1962-1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - The Nation., 1953-1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - O'Casey, Sean, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 3A)
    - Judy Polumbaum From China., 1979-1981 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Paul Robeson., 1956-1965 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Bill Reuben's Archive / Information On Rosenberg Case., 1979-1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - South American Refugees., 1977-1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - South Paddington Labour Party Correspondence., 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Third World / Tercer Mundo., 1979-1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Claude and Joyce Williams., 1938-1967 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Claude and Joyce Williams., 1968-1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Claude and Joyce Williams., 1973-1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Claude and Joyce Williams., undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Claude Williams Research File., 1943-1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Asa Zatz., 1982-1986 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Subseries II:C: General Correspondence - Countries, 1937-1989
    - Africa., 1940-1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Asia., 1937-1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Australia/New Zealand., 1963-1972 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Caribbean and Central America., 1961-1966 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Caribbean and Central America., 1967-1986 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Canada., 1961-1985 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Europe., 1938-1987 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Ireland/United Kingdom., 1939-1972 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Ireland/United Kingdom., 1973-1986 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Mexico., 1963-1972 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Mexico., 1973-1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Mexico., undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - South America., 1962-1985 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - United States., 1942-1964 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - United States., 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - United States., 1968-1973 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - United States., 1974-1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - United States., 1979-1982 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - United States., 1983-1989 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - United States., undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Series III: Political Activities, 1944-1989
  Political Activities contains three subseries: Belfrage's press control activity in Germany, his deportation, and the National Guardian. The Germany section is the smallest, containing mostly travel orders from the U.S. Army (see also unpublished writings, circa 1947, for two short manuscripts on this topic). The deportation section is the largest and contains mostly articles about Belfrage, correspondence, and legal documents from his case. There are a few articles here about Russian espionage charges against Belfrage (1949) (see obituaries for a discussion of these charges). The National Guardian section mostly contains correspondence, articles by Belfrage, and his notes on the events covered in the paper (see also Something to Guard, Belfrage and Aronson's book about the National Guardian in the writings section). There is a fair amount of documentation on the founding and early years of the paper, and a brief but important series of letters from 1967 that chronicle Belfrage and Aronson's resignation from the paper.
  - Subseries III:A: German Press Control, 1944-1946
    - Psychological Warfare Division (Pwd), Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force (Shaef)., 1944-1945 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - U.S. Army and German Newspapers., 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 6, Box Shared Tamiment 043)
  - Subseries III:B: Deportation, 1944-1989
    - Government records of C.B.'s political activities and writings., ca.1949 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Foreign press articles on C.B.'s Espionage charges., 1949 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - C.B.'s Arrest and deportation case: Congressional Record, National Guardian Press Releases, Notes., 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Jim Aronson and C.B.'s testimony before Committee On Government Operations., 1953 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - British articles on C.B.'s arrest and deportation case., 1953 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Portrait of an Undesirable Alien: article about C.B. by Frank Scully., ca.1953 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Meeting to Defend C.B. Speeches., 1953 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Sermon on C.B.'s deportation at Holy Trinity Church in Brooklyn., 1953 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - House Unamerican Activities Committee hearing., 1953 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Jim Aronson and C.B.'s testimonies before the State Permanent Subcommittee On Investigations of The Committee On Government Operations., 1953 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - C.B.'s arrest for deportation: Warrant, notes, article., 1953 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - C.B.'s speech for Nassau Co. American Labor Party dinner., 1953 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Deportation case notes., 1953-1955 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Arrest and Deportation Case: legal documentation., 1953-1955 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Deportation case: U.S. Court of Appeals briefs., 1953-1955 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - C.B. writings in jail., 1953-1955 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Deportation Case: articles., 1953-1955 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Deportation Case: articles from National Guardian., 1954-1955 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Federal Detention Headquarters: record of C.B.'s belongings., 1955 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Speech in defense of C.B. (by Jim Aronson?)., ca.1955 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - The Case of the Stubborn Editor: pamphlet on deportation., 1955 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Questions from deportation hearings., 1955 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - The American Tradition: extracts from C.B.'s address at Conway Hall, London. September, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Interview and Meikeljohn Institute Symposium; speech on American inquisition and deportation experience., ca.1980 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Espionage accusations: articles and correspondence., 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Deportation case and jail correspondence., 1949-1953, undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Deportation case and jail correspondence. June, 1953-1958 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Subseries III:C: National Guardian, 1948-1987
    - Founding of the National Guardian., 1948 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Editorials for a new P.M.; About Wallace presidential campaign., ca.1948 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - National Guardian; Subscriptions and loans., 1948-1951 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Noel Field: correspondence., 1948-1951 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - C.B. Letter to Jack Mcmanus regarding political differences., 1949 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Notes on a political line for the Guardian.., ca.1949 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Peoples Party of Connecticut dinner, notes for a speech by C.B., 1950 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Chronology of events reported in the National Guardian., 1945-1959 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Early National Guardian Writers and chronology of events., 1948-1955 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - A Dissenting Newspaper In The U.S.A. by C.B., 1956 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Speeches by C.B. for National Guardian dinners., 1956, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - National Guardian; articles by and about C.B., 1954-1967 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence From National Guardian readers., 1963-1966 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Memories and convictions by Jim Aronson, Nation article on National Guardian's Origins., 1968 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Chronology of "Negro 'Cases' and Lynchings"., ca.1970 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - The split at the Liberated Guardian., 1972 (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - C.B. and Jim Aronson's resignation from The Guardian correspondence., 1967 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - " National Guardian: A History" by C.B. and J.A., and essay on The Guardian by J.A., ca.1974 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Guardian correspondence., 1948-1983 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Guardian correspondence with C.B., Guardian Book reviews and articles by C.B., ca.1984-1987 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - "The Birth of The National Gazette" (by C.B.?)., undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - National Guardian Journalism notes., undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - National Guardian; international contact list., undated (Box 9, Folder 23)
- Series IV: Writings, 1927-1990
  Writings contains 12 subseries. The first consists of published and unpublished articles, travel notes, and translations. There is substantial documentation of Belfrage's two trips to Cuba (1961-1962 & 1975-1977), including notes, articles and correspondence. There is a long correspondence with Belfrage's friend and colleague, Eduardo Galeano about Belfrage's translation of his trilogy, Memory of Fire.
  Several sub-series document Cedric's published book projects and contains typescripts, correspondence and research files. There is a large section of writing and correspondence for the section of Belfrage's book, The Frightened Giant (about his deportation) called, The Admiral (1955-1965). This is about Scotty MacKenzie, who posed as a Naval admiral for many years, whom Belfrage met in jail. There is also a substantial section of Something to Guard materials, mostly reviews, notes and correspondence (1974-1980). The American Inquisition is the largest section (three linear feet). It consists mostly of research files which contain Belfrage's notes and source material. One linear foot exclusively contains information on the case of Miami lawyer Leo Sheiner who was taken before the Florida Supreme Court for alleged Communist Party affiliations, and on the `Red Cases' of several Miami residents taken before the House Un-American Activities Committee for the same reason. There is also a great deal of research on the atomic espionage cases of Ethel and Julius Rosenberg and Morton Sobell. The American Inquisition section documents Belfrage's 1973 publicity tour in the U.S., his first time back since his deportation in 1955, and his continuing campaign to obtain visas to visit the U.S.
  Other sub-series contain unpublished writings. They are mostly book projects, but there are also numerous shorter pieces. The two longest projects are his book on Owen Whitfield and Thad Snow (Belfrage's fictional name for Owen Whitfield is Hugh Goodrum), and his Hollywood book and memoir. The Hollywood section contains many of Belfrage's articles as a film critic, manuscripts of chapters, and a small amount of correspondence and source material. There is also a short general memoir project including chapter notes on people who played influential roles in his life and an autobiographical outline. Most of the shorter pieces are light-hearted, humorous spoofs on miscellaneous topics. There are also two short manuscripts on Belfrages' German press control activities (circa 1947).
  - Subseries IV:A: Travel Notes, 1956-1977
    - Travel notes from Russia., 1956 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Travel notes from Ghana and Rome., 1957 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Travel notes from China and correspondence., 1957-1958 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Afro-Asian Peoples' Solidarity Conference in Cairo; Notes and articles., 1958 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Travel notes from Israel., 1959 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Articles by C.B. Written during Cuba trip., 1961 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Travel notes from Cuba., 1961-1962 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Travel notes from the West Indies., 1963 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence about Cuba., 1964-1966 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Travel notes from Ussr, Hungary and Germany., 1966 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Rosa Hilda Zell; Correspondence from Cuba., 1965-1971 (Box 10, Folder 11)